<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Thoughts in the cloud</title><link href="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/feeds/internet-of-things.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://mindinthecloud.github.io/</id><updated>2017-03-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>In the Internet of Things, the consumer is not a customer but a supplier</title><link href="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/2017/03/IoT-a-paradigm-shift/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><author><name>Joram Teusink</name></author><id>tag:mindinthecloud.github.io,2017-03-09:2017/03/IoT-a-paradigm-shift/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the soon-to-be world in which everything is connected to everything, we will face quite some (unforeseen) challenges. One of those challenges is related to the protection of privacy and security of the system as a whole. The other one is the role of the consumer. To quickly sum it up in a single&amp;nbsp;statement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
In the Internet of Things, the consumer is not (only) a customer but (also) a supplier.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post we will focus on why we make this statement and why we think this new paradigm holds true. We will talk about the fundamental shift in the way we think, or should think, about data and&amp;nbsp;privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="/images/IoE-paradigm-shift.png" /&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="you-own-your-devices"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;You own your&amp;nbsp;devices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounds rather plausible, right? And it is. Because with every device you buy you take on the responsibility of owning it. Whether it is connected to anything beyond the power cord or not, by paying the bill you accepted the ownership of the &amp;#8216;thing&amp;#8217;. This has many consequences, but we´ll first address the issue of data&amp;nbsp;ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="do-you-own-the-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do you own the&amp;nbsp;data?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the device you bought is connected to a data network. Not exactly a mental stretch with a &amp;#8216;thing&amp;#8217; we refer to as a device in the &amp;#8216;&lt;em&gt;Internet&lt;/em&gt; of Things&amp;#8217;. This device will generate or accumulate data. This might be simple sensory data or more complex data structures that describe behavioral patterns. It tells something about who you are and what you do. This data is often considered sensitive or at least personal. In the near future, this will certainly extend to data we have not yet dared to dream&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, this data may be your thermostat that is building up a profile of your presence and the temperature of your room or your &amp;#8216;smart&amp;#8217; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; that is building up a profile of what you like to watch. Another popular application is home security, such as video-cameras that continuously register what is going on in your most private environment. Which is by the way an &lt;em&gt;intrusion to your privacy&lt;/em&gt; that the police and intelligence agencies are only allowed to with a legal warrant. All this collected data is privacy sensitive. It becomes even more sensitive when combined with data that is collected by other devices you may own or services you&amp;nbsp;use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This data is valuable for you. Or at least it should be. Most people do not want their conversations with their lovers to be openly shared across social media &amp;#8212; especially not if that conversation is spiced with photographic material of a certain private nature. But that is not the only data that is valuable. Almost all data about you should be valuable to you and treated as sensitive. &amp;#8220;Why?&amp;#8221; you might ask. &lt;em&gt;Because this data can be used to influence you&lt;/em&gt;. Your data is being used in ways that cause no direct damage, at least no damage that you could easily identify. But the way you are being influenced is not necessarily in your direct interest; it is primarily aimed at increasing the profit of some&amp;nbsp;company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies are willing to spend substantial money to get access to this data. Because they can use it to tailor their ways of influencing your behavior, which is the very nature of&amp;nbsp;advertisements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many business models in which large corporations get access to your sensitive data. But for now, we will stick to the one that is the easiest to grasp and is the basic premise that most people base their use of data-collecting devices&amp;nbsp;on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
You own the devices; therefore, you are the owner of all data that is collected by these devices.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="are-you-selling-your-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Are you selling your&amp;nbsp;data?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now follow us in the next step. You own and operate devices that collects data about you. What are you doing with this&amp;nbsp;data?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you use devices that collect all this data, both of which you own, do you use them commercially? It depends a bit on the privacy policies you agreed upon with the supplier of the services, but the answer to this is very likely a &amp;#8220;yes&amp;#8221;. Even when you are just an individual and not a company. This may not be the way you look at it now, so let us explain we make this&amp;nbsp;statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most likely you share this data with a company, in exchange for a service or an &amp;#8216;enhanced experience&amp;#8217; as they so exquisitely frame it. This company may be the one that built the device or provided it to you; frequently these things are bundled it with an on-line service directly coupled with the device. It may be a third party, which uses the data to enhance your experience of the device or to provide additional (value adding) services. In both cases, you provide data in exchange for a&amp;nbsp;service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually this can be characterized as one of four types of supplier-customer&amp;nbsp;relations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have paid for the service with a one-time fee with the purchase of the device. This usually covers a limited period of time, although this is rarely made explicit. Degradation of service over time is almost guaranteed; the older the device, the flakier support tends to become. Your smartphone or tablet are likely the most explanatory&amp;nbsp;examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You pay a recurring subscription fee, which is usually supposed to cover all operational costs of the service provider. This model is the traditional pay-as-you-go service model that has been around since way before the internet was conceived and is still the most viable for the supplier in the long&amp;nbsp;term.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You do not pay any monetary fees, but your usage of the services adds to the momentum and user base for the service provider´s paid services which cover for the cost of the free services as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You do not pay any monetary fees, but allow the service provider to use your data to build profiles that it will monetize to its own discretion, i.e. targeted advertising. In this case is covered by the adage &lt;em&gt;¨if you don´t pay for the product, you&lt;/em&gt; are &lt;em&gt;the product¨&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, whether it is in exchange for money or not, you actually trade (sell) your&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-does-this-effect-your-position-in-the-supply-chain"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How does this effect your position in the ´supply&amp;nbsp;chain´?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our argumentation up to this point can be summarized in three&amp;nbsp;statements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you own the&amp;nbsp;IoT-device;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you own the data it&amp;nbsp;collects;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you trade the&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you own stuff that collects or generates data and you trade it with a company, you are essentially a &lt;em&gt;service provider&lt;/em&gt;. You are the supplier of your data, and you sell it in exchange for either money, features or services! The other party is the consumer, since it &amp;#8216;consumes&amp;#8217; your data. This might sound very silly or strange, so let us explain why we think this holds&amp;nbsp;true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="loweralpha simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a supplier who sells IoT-devices. It supplies you with equipment, with &amp;#8216;things&amp;#8217;. When you buy something, you are the&amp;nbsp;customer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upon enabling the IoT-device to provide data to the supplier&amp;#8217;s services –or those of a third party– you become a supplier yourself: a supplier of data to be&amp;nbsp;precise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your customer is in many cases the supplier of your device (the equipment), now in the role of the one who is utilizing your&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in this situation you are performing four&amp;nbsp;roles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the customer in buying the&amp;nbsp;device;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the supplier of data by trading your data with your&amp;nbsp;customer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the customer in paying for services which utilize the data generated by the&amp;nbsp;device;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the consumer of the&amp;nbsp;services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally we only think about #1 and #4 and consider them as one single role. This has the consequence that role #2 is obscured; it is rarely more than an afterthought when even considered at all. That is why we strongly believe the paradigm shift is needed, or to the very least should be&amp;nbsp;debated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because you as a customer also perform role #2, we can&amp;nbsp;state:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
In the world of IoT, the consumer (of a device) is a supplier (of data).&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-consumer-as-data-supplier-privacy-considerations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The consumer as data supplier: privacy&amp;nbsp;considerations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you consider the data flow we described as a supply chain, you make the shift from a customer/consumer-centric view to a set of demand-supply relations that is very common in the corporate world. And if you are familiar with data protection in this context, you might get a little itchy. Because this viewpoint has quite some implications for accountability and liability regarding data protection and&amp;nbsp;security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a company and selling data to a data consumer (your customer), you are required to do at least four&amp;nbsp;things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;specify the Terms of Use for the&amp;nbsp;data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;obtain consent of the data subjects (the individuals about whom you collect data) to this Terms of&amp;nbsp;Use;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cover the use of this data by a legally binding agreement with your&amp;nbsp;customer;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;take every reasonable precaution to ensure that the data is only used by authorized parties and only for the intended purpose for which it has been collected. This is the topic of Information Security and&amp;nbsp;Privacy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These obligations are all within the scope of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; General Data Protection Regulation (a.k.a. the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDPR&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are an individual, requirement #2 may be considered as implicitly satisfied since the data subject is the very same entity that provides the data. This does in no way limit your responsibility regarding data protection (requirement #4). It is just rather difficult to sue yourself for inadequate performance or&amp;nbsp;non-compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when you provide services with collected data about other subjects that you do not legally represent, this (at least theoretically) can get very ugly very quick. If you want to make it really complicated, you might add another ingredient to this cocktail: the right to be forgotten that is embedded in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDPR&lt;/span&gt;. But that´s another topic for someone with a legal&amp;nbsp;background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ll now step into the complications of requirement #4: the obligation to protect the security of the data you collect and&amp;nbsp;distribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="ownership-of-a-device-the-obligations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ownership of a device: the&amp;nbsp;obligations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, you purchased a device and connected it to The Internet of Everything. As we have shown before you have now become a service provider. You are going to provide data to your customer. Data that will probably have privacy-sensitive characteristics, so you are required to protect this data from unauthorized access and&amp;nbsp;use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="maintenace-burden"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Maintenace&amp;nbsp;burden&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By paying the bill you accepted the ownership of the &amp;#8216;thing&amp;#8217;. In doing so you made yourself accountable for all benefits and costs that come with the simple existence of the &amp;#8216;thing&amp;#8217;. You are not only &amp;#8216;responsible&amp;#8217; for reaping the benefits but also for the burden of operations and maintenance during its entire life cycle. Even if you manage to outsource this, which for consumer grade IoT is not (yet) likely, if at all possible, in the end you stay&amp;nbsp;accountable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="security"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you own the device and you own the data, then you are responsible for its security. No one else but you, really! European privacy legislation is based on this very principle. Whether you generate Personal Identifiable Information (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PII&lt;/span&gt;) or are the custodian of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PII&lt;/span&gt; that is trusted to you by its subject (the individual about whom the data has been collected), you are what the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDPR&lt;/span&gt; calls the &amp;#8216;processor&amp;#8217; and ultimately accountable for the entire supply&amp;nbsp;chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="privacy"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Privacy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could collapse role #2 (the supplier of data) with role #4 (the consumer of the processed data). If we consider it this way, the device owner (being both supplier and consumer) outsources a part of the data processing. Probably to the provider of &amp;#8216;value adding services&amp;#8217;. At least the Dutch Privacy legislation requires you to cover this processing with a legally binding Data Processing Agreement (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DPA&lt;/span&gt;). This should specify the responsibilities (not the accountability) transferred to third parties. You mandate other companies to handle data you are responsible for. You set constraints on the exact &amp;#8216;processing activities&amp;#8217; that will be performed and the conditions under which they will do&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least that is the theory. We all know that only in theory there is no difference between theory and practice; in practice, there is. But alas, it is not only the theory but also the&amp;nbsp;law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But consumers buying things and using services accompanied with them do not sign such &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DPA&lt;/span&gt; with their third parties. At best, they accept the Terms of Service that govern such services. And let’s hope that is not an instance of what we call &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.thebiggestlie.com"&gt;&amp;#8216;the biggest lie on the internet&amp;#8217;&lt;/a&gt;: they click a checkbox stating something like &amp;#8220;I have read the (&amp;#8230;) and accept to be bound by this&amp;#8221; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://medium.com/enrique-dans/the-biggest-lie-on-the-internet-i-have-read-and-understood-the-terms-of-service-54c7b2f77440"&gt;without reading the text&lt;/a&gt; . &lt;em&gt;It is quite likely that these terms of service just contain a full waiver to the service provider for all responsibilities that should be contained in a Data Processing&amp;nbsp;Agreement.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="where-the-snake-bites-its-own-tail"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where the snake bites its own&amp;nbsp;tail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have the situation where the consumer remains ultimately responsible for data processing that he has completely outsourced. Even worse: processing has been outsourced in a way that has essentially stripped him from any control over&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In your role as a consumer of services, you subscribe to a service using your &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PII&lt;/span&gt;. You agree that this service provider will be processing your sensitive data. You would require adequate protection of this valuable data. But your service provider has outsourced the data collection process to a party that is unable to adequately protect this data as it is generated, collected, stored and transferred. This would be unacceptable because the supplier is violating the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDPR&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in this case, you are the data provider yourself. You as a service consumer agree that the service is delivered by an unreliable data provider and therefore you cannot hold the service provider accountable for any consequence of this data provider failing. Ridiculous if a third party were involved, but legally valid if you are the data provider&amp;nbsp;yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way we look at the Internet of Things &amp;#8212;especially in the consumer domain&amp;#8212; needs a fundamental change in perspective. If we consider the data flow generated by IoT-devices as a supply chain, we make the shift from a customer/consumer-centric view to a set of demand-supply relations. This is a rather uncomfortable position, because it has quite some implications for accountability and liability regarding data protection and&amp;nbsp;security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time consumers (including ourselves) are not acting in alignment with the roles that this viewpoint uncovers. We end up being service providers who are completely responsible for data protection over the entire supply chain. Yet our customers and suppliers are usually not bound to any obligations to protect this data. And we lack the tools to do it properly&amp;nbsp;ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking of IoT as a chain of demand-supply relations may help to identify systemic weaknesses. It may turn out to be a good start for finding effective strategies to fight the undesirable exploitation of these&amp;nbsp;weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="about-the-authors"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;About the&amp;nbsp;authors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jrm.tsnk.nl/"&gt;Joram Teusink&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rickveenstra/"&gt;Rick Veenstra&lt;/a&gt; are both Information Security Officers and close&amp;nbsp;friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#id1"&gt;&lt;span class="problematic" id="id2"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Repost on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.teusink.eu/2017/03/in-iot-consumer-is-supplier.html"&gt;teusink.eu&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message" id="id1"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WARNING&lt;/span&gt;/2 (&lt;tt class="docutils"&gt;/home/rick/CloudStation/Documents/blog/content/Internet of Things/IoT-a paradigm shift.rst&lt;/tt&gt;, line 150); &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="#id2"&gt;backlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Inline emphasis start-string without end-string.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="IoT"></category><category term="privacy"></category><category term="concepts"></category></entry><entry><title>The roles of the owner of an IoT device, expressed in UML</title><link href="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/2016/10/the-roles-of-the-owner-of-an-iot-device-expressed-in-uml/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-20T00:00:00+02:00</published><author><name>Rick Veenstra</name></author><id>tag:mindinthecloud.github.io,2016-10-20:2016/10/the-roles-of-the-owner-of-an-iot-device-expressed-in-uml/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a previous blog post we mentioned the different roles of the consumer owning an IoT device. In this article we will try to illustrate these roles in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UML&lt;/span&gt; Use Case diagrams. The Use Case diagram is one of the several types of models that are part of the Unified Modeling Language (see wikipedia). These are used to describe the interactions of actors with a piece of&amp;nbsp;software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will start with the most basic model. An actor (the consumer) uses a service (via an internet connection). This service is provided by &amp;#8212;you guessed it&amp;#8212; a service&amp;nbsp;provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="uml diagram" class="uml" src="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/images/5cea17f3.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty basic, even if you are not into &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UML&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step we add the fact that the service depends on data provided by the consumer. He now has two roles: that of the user of the service and that of the provider of data. In the Use Case diagram we show this by adding the role above the icon of each&amp;nbsp;actor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="uml diagram" class="uml" src="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/images/411b5d41.png" /&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-role-consumer"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The role &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8216;consumer&amp;#8217;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For someone who is used to talk about services in a software context, a little confusion creeps in. The label &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8216;consumer&amp;#8217;&lt;/em&gt; in an economical/marketing context is quite clear. It is used for individual people purchasing goods. In the world of digital services, the label &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8216;consumer&amp;#8217;&lt;/em&gt; is used in a more generic way. In this case it is used for any object (usually some kind of software) that uses the output of a service. Since we somewhat blend these two meanings we will now use the name &amp;#8220;John Doe&amp;#8221; for the individual that uses services in the Internet of Things. One of his &lt;em&gt;roles&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;service consumer&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the diagrams. The data provided by the customer (now identified as &amp;#8220;John Doe&amp;#8221;) is stored and processed by the Service. These are two separate activities, so we model the service as a&amp;nbsp;group:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="uml diagram" class="uml" src="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/images/b9fa54df.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have a basic model of a generic service that is provided over the internet by a service provider, that depends on data provided by the end&amp;nbsp;user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="data-processing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data&amp;nbsp;processing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ll add one additional element. In the previous diagram John Doe uses &amp;#8216;data processing&amp;#8217;. While technically correct, an average John Doe is not likely attracted to use &amp;#8216;data processing&amp;#8217;. In business manegement lingo, the service provides &amp;#8216;added value&amp;#8217; to John Doe; something (not strictly defined) that he recognises as having value for&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="uml diagram" class="uml" src="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/images/cc856137.png" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="paying-for-the-service"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Paying for the&amp;nbsp;service&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, you apparently are still with us. Up to this point things have been straight forward. Now we add somthing a little complicating. No service can exisist on it&amp;#8217;s own. Providing a service comes at a cost. In the context of digital services and the Internet of Things this at least requires computer equipment and network connections. So we factor in than John Doe pays the Service Provider for delivering the&amp;nbsp;service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="uml diagram" class="uml" src="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/images/cb7d6d51.png" /&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="sidestep-paying-for-a-free-service"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sidestep: paying for a free&amp;nbsp;service?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you may object: I&amp;#8217;m using quite a lot of web applications that I do not have to pay for. Say
Google, Twitter, Facebook, you name &amp;#8216;em. So why adding this last step? Well, There is a lot to say
about &amp;#8216;free&amp;#8217; services. That is subject for another post (or even a series). But let me assure you:
you are actually paying for these services, one way or another. It might not be by actually
transfering money (as with subscription based services), but you are generating value for the service
provider while using the&amp;nbsp;service:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your usage of the services adds to the momentum and userbase for the service provider´s
paid services which cover for the cost of the free services as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You generate content you license to the provider (this happens more often than you think;
read the fine print in the end user agreements or whatever fancy name they gave these legal&amp;nbsp;statements).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You allow the service provider to use your data to build profiles that it will monetize to its
own discretion, i.e. targeted advertising. This case is covered by the saying &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;if you don´t pay f
or the product, you&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;are&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;the product&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;. Usually this involves Personally Identifiable
Information (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PII&lt;/span&gt; for&amp;nbsp;short).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reasoning implies that we need to add another role for our dear John Doe: the data&amp;nbsp;subject&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="uml diagram" class="uml" src="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/images/95597d25.png" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="next-how-the-data-is-generated"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next: How the data is&amp;nbsp;generated&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have described a model for a generic service that is using data provided by the consumer, John Doe. This model can be applied to many web applications. The data is usually generated interactively by the user via the application&amp;#8217;s web interface, from another application using a published &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; or by means of an app on a mobile device. But what we call the &amp;#8216;Internet of Things&amp;#8217; extends this model. Human interaction is replaced by smart devices that autonomously generate&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-device"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;device&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will first focus on the device and leave the service out (for&amp;nbsp;now).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="uml diagram" class="uml" src="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/images/9cb82da1.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again a very basic start, but not for&amp;nbsp;long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="sidestep-the-device-and-it-s-software-a-k-a-firmware"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sidestep: The device and it&amp;#8217;s software a.k.a.&amp;nbsp;firmware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All devices in the Internet of Things are built as a combination of hardware and software. The time that his software was &amp;#8216;burned&amp;#8217; into the hardware and could only be changed by physically interacting with the hardware has long gone by. The original &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EPROM"&gt;EPROMs&lt;/a&gt; could only be reprogrammed after erasing them by exposing the hardware to strong ultraviolet light. The introduction of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EEPROM"&gt;EEPROMs&lt;/a&gt; allowed electronic equipment to be reprogrammed electronically. Now nearly all devices have substantial amounts of non-volatile memory that holds the software that control the device&amp;#8217;s functions. This software can be usually be replaced remotely; the process is called &amp;#8216;flashing&amp;#8217;, named after &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flash_memory"&gt;the type of memory involved&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-maintenance-burden"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The maintenance&amp;nbsp;burden&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every device man has created requires maintenance. It&amp;#8217;s the law. Not a legal one, but a law of nature. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_law_of_thermodynamics"&gt;The second law of thermodynamics&lt;/a&gt; to be precise. Everything in the universe tends to &amp;#8216;a state of maximum entropy&amp;#8217;, which is a physics scholar&amp;#8217;s lingo for &amp;#8216;chaos&amp;#8217;. We all experience this daily: everything eventually breaks in parts. If you wait long enough, these parts break into smaller and smaller chunks, until only atoms are left. At least, that&amp;#8217;s the simplified version of the&amp;nbsp;theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, you&amp;#8217;ll have to wait a veeeeeery long time before your device turns into dust, but you get the picture. Anything man creates will degrade over time. Ignore your housecleaning chores long enough and your furniture will get covered with dust. We all have experience with electronic devices getting to behave erratic or not at all. We can&amp;#8217;t prevent this degradation but we can (try to) postpone it by regular maintenance. Therefore our cars (mostly) get regular oil changes and while the tires evetually wear out we try to keep them balanced and sufficiently&amp;nbsp;inflated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This maintenance burden comes with the ownership of &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; device. For a device in the world of IoT this burden comes in two areas: firmware and configuration. Firmware is actually just software, but tightly coupled to the hardware. Firmware is usually not intended to be installed or modified by the owner of the device as we are used to with our desktops and laptops. Depending of the functionality it has configuration settings that can be changed by the owner or user of the &amp;#8216;thing&amp;#8217;. Configuration requires at least a basic understanding of the usage of the device and can be done&amp;nbsp;wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our diagram we have to add the same actor John Doe a second time, but now in his new role of &amp;#8220;device&amp;nbsp;maintainer&amp;#8221;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="uml diagram" class="uml" src="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/images/e7c260a4.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As most of us know by now, software is rarely flawless. See &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.cs.tau.ac.il/~nachumd/horror.html"&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt; for some horror stories. Updating the operating system of our computers has become an annoying but unavoidable part of our digital lives. The same is (or better: should be) true for the semi-autonomous devices in the Internet of Things. One major problem is that software flaws or bugs are not always repaired. Once a device is sold, there is not much of an incentive for a device maker to maintain its software beyond the period the devices are actually being sold. Yet, in our diagram we need to add the maintanance of the device. Someone at least has to provide updated software to users of these&amp;nbsp;devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So again we need a new role: the &amp;#8220;firmware supplier&amp;#8221;. Usually this role is performed by the IoT device&amp;nbsp;supplier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="uml diagram" class="uml" src="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/images/cc408099.png" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-whole-picture"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The whole&amp;nbsp;picture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it is time to combine the two diagrams we&amp;nbsp;constructed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="uml diagram" class="uml" src="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/images/8d5f3a30.png" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We just created a diagram showing the different roles involved in the use of a &amp;#8216;thing&amp;#8217; in the Internet of Things. A device that gathers data about someone and uses a service to process the data for the owner into something that he percieves as valuable. What at first observation appears to be very simple, evolves into a model in which &lt;em&gt;John Doe performs no less than&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;five&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;different roles&lt;/em&gt;. And poor John thought he had only bought himself a&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8216;thing&amp;#8217;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="IoT"></category><category term="UML"></category></entry><entry><title>The key overlap and the gap: IoT and IoS</title><link href="https://mindinthecloud.github.io/2016/05/the-key-overlap-and-the-gap-iot-and-ios/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-05-07T00:00:00+02:00</published><author><name>Rick Veenstra</name></author><id>tag:mindinthecloud.github.io,2016-05-07:2016/05/the-key-overlap-and-the-gap-iot-and-ios/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The buzz around the &amp;#8216;Internet of Things&amp;#8217; is mainly caused because we seem
to have passed a major tipping point. Cheap to produce Systems-on-a-Chip
have reached levels of integration and computing power that enable running
serious functionality combined with a full &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IP&lt;/span&gt; network stack. We&amp;#8217;re facing
an explosion of inter-networked things. These things have mainly been
extensions of concepts we have been familiar with for decades. Heart-rate
monitors are not exactly a new idea; the form-factor of a watch and network
connectivity have just extended a concept we&amp;#8217;ve already known for decades.
The same with security cameras, thermostats and light bulbs. But that is
going to change rapidly. Who knows what brillant or downright amazing
solutions will be conceived for problems we didn&amp;#8217;t know we&amp;nbsp;had&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the other side there has been an explosion of internet applications that
can be accessed using well-defined and publicly available APIs. A myrad
of interconnected applications has become available in recent years, mashed
together like never&amp;nbsp;before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="where-iot-and-ios-meet"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where IoT and IoS&amp;nbsp;meet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where the internet of things (IoT) and the internet of services
(IoS) connect. These things are sensors, information processors and devices
that enable interaction with the physical world. But their potential value
is only really unleashed when their data and functionality is processed and
enhanced by services. Sevices that are provided as web applications, more and
more extended with a user interface built as an app for your&amp;nbsp;smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases these services are provided by the same company that sold you
the device. Your purchase included these services; in fact a part of the
bill covered the cost of the services. You paid a one-time fee. But many of
these devices have a well-documented interface that can be handled by other
services as well. Services that are extremely cheap or even&amp;nbsp;free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="but"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But&amp;#8230;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Services have to be provided. Providing a service is an activity that
requires funding, significant funding. Equipment, people and resources
are still not avalable for free, at least not in countries that
participate in the global economy. Providing a service has to create
benefits for the provider. Tangible benefits such as monetary value or
cash flow. Or intangible benefits, such as knowledge, a change in
behaviour of people, future monetary benefits or whatever people may
deem valuable. Companies are very creative in finding ways to generate
financial revenues from these intangible benefits. There are myrads of services
that require no fee from its users. But you nevertheless pay for them, in many
cases by trading the one thing that has value to these companies. The one and
only thing that only you can create and that does not require
real effort: data about your and about your&amp;nbsp;behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A service has a limited lifespan. Once you stop interacting with a service,
it will cease to create benefits for the provider. If the provider terminates
the service, it will cease to create benefits. If the provider ceases to
exist and the service is not tranfered to another provider, the service
will end and cease to create&amp;nbsp;benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the data the service has gathered remain valuable for the
service provider. Regardless of rights the provider has establised in
the terms of service, this value will degrade rapidly over&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-ios-generates-the-value-of-iot"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The IoS generates the value of&amp;nbsp;IoT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One could consider a &amp;#8216;thing&amp;#8217; in the context of the Internet of Things as
something that provides one or more services. The consumer of this service
usually is some other kind of &amp;#8216;service&amp;#8217; in the Internet of Services. So
while the device that collects the data (the actual &amp;#8216;thing&amp;#8217; in IoT) may be a
tangible object one can touch, cherish and throw out of the window, most
of its value is generated not by the device itself but by the services
it is connected to: the Internet of Services. Those services have a
lifespan that is only rather loosely related to the device. It is
mostly determined by the ways the service provider is able to
generate monetary benefits from these&amp;nbsp;service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="IoT"></category></entry></feed>