<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Mind in the cloud</title><link href="http://localhost:8000/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://localhost:8000/feeds/personal-development.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://localhost:8000/</id><updated>2013-02-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Lessons from Benjamin Zander's talk on TED 2008</title><link href="http://localhost:8000/2013/02/lessons-from-benjamin-zanders-talk-on-ted-2008/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-02-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><author><name>Rick Veenstra</name></author><id>tag:localhost:8000,2013-02-09:2013/02/lessons-from-benjamin-zanders-talk-on-ted-2008/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Zander is a world-famous classical orchestra conductor.
During &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ted.com/talks/benjamin_zander_on_music_and_passion.html"&gt;his talk at TED2008 on 'classical music and passion'&lt;/a&gt; he refers to
a moment of 'enlightenment' as I would call it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was 45 years old, I'd been conducting for 20 years, and I suddenly
had a realization. The conductor of an orchestra doesn't make a
sound. (...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He depends, for his power, on his ability to make other people
powerful. And that changed everything for me. It was totally life
changing. (...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized my job was to awaken possibility in other people. And of
course, I wanted to know whether I was doing that. And you know how
you find out? You look at their eyes. If their eyes are shining, you
know you're doing it. (...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the eyes are not shining, you get to ask a question. And this is
the question: who am I being, that my players' eyes are not shining?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow, now that's what I would call enlightenment. &amp;quot;My job is to awaken
possibility is other people&amp;quot;. That resonates with me, deep inside.
Servant leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benjamin extends this insight to parenthood, generalizes this to his
vision of succes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can do that with our children, too. Who am I being, that my
children's eyes are not shining? That's a totally different world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you know, I have a definition of success. For me, it's very
simple. It's not about wealth and fame and power. It's about how
many shining eyes I have around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice how he phrases this. It's not &amp;quot;how am I &lt;em&gt;behaving&lt;/em&gt;, that their
eyes are not shining?&amp;quot; but &amp;quot;how am I &lt;strong&gt;being&lt;/strong&gt;?&amp;quot; That's a far deeper way
to look at it. Fundamental. Existential. &amp;quot;Who am I &lt;strong&gt;being&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;? Who can I
&lt;strong&gt;be&lt;/strong&gt; for others so that their eyes are shining?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question shifts our focus. It's not primarily about &lt;strong&gt;doing&lt;/strong&gt;, it's
all about &lt;strong&gt;being&lt;/strong&gt;. Because who we are is the source of our doing. Our
identity, our views of who we are and our purpose in life, is the driver
for all that we do. It also shifts our focus from ourselves to the
other. Though we ask what &lt;strong&gt;we&lt;/strong&gt; are being, we define that in terms of
our impact on others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who am I being...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that my spouse's eyes are not shining?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that my children's eyes are not shining?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that my colleague's eyes are not shining?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that my team's eyes are not shining?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that my congregation's eyes are not shining?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and we can extend this question to each and every relation we have in
this life.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="ted"></category><category term="faith"></category></entry></feed>