<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Mind in the cloud</title><link href="http://localhost:8000/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://localhost:8000/feeds/random-ramblings.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://localhost:8000/</id><updated>2013-01-28T21:30:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Now</title><link href="http://localhost:8000/2013/01/now/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-01-28T21:30:00+01:00</published><author><name>Rick Veenstra</name></author><id>tag:localhost:8000,2013-01-28:2013/01/now/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday is closed, finished, done. Nothing can be changed about what is passed. Whatever has happened stays happened. Forever. Only our memories can change. And they &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; change, that's for sure. Because every time we revisit a memory we are in fact &lt;em&gt;re-creating&lt;/em&gt; it, &lt;em&gt;re-shaping&lt;/em&gt; it, changing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow is uncertain. What we 'know for sure' about tomorrow is nothing more than an extrapolation of our past experiences. Which are uncertain by themselves, since our memories are volatile and unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Yesterday is a memory, tomorrow is a dream; today is a gift, that's why it's called &amp;quot;present&amp;quot;.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing we have is today, now. Actually not even that much; all we have is just this very moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter the circumstances or events that got us here. No matter whether we like it or not. No matter the path behind us or the path before us. We are right here, right now, and that's all we have. That's what we have to deal with, that's what we have to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;these circumstances; comfortable, hard or even painful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;these people, whether we like them or not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this task, this job, this resonsibility, this opportunity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever we may posess, whatever influence we may think we have, bottom line is that we have very little. Just now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now what? What are you going to do with what you do have?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;There's nothin' behind me and nothin' that ties me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;To somethin' that might have been true yesterday&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tomorrow is open, right now it seems to be more than enough&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;to just be here today&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.metrolyrics.com/sweet-surrender-lyrics-john-denver.html"&gt;John Denver - Sweet Surrender&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</summary><category term="quotes"></category></entry><entry><title>Every successful enterprise requires three men...</title><link href="http://localhost:8000/2013/01/Every_successful_enterprise_requires_three_men/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-01-26T11:20:00+01:00</published><author><name>Rick Veenstra</name></author><id>tag:localhost:8000,2013-01-26:2013/01/Every_successful_enterprise_requires_three_men/</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--  --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Every successful enterprise requires three men - a
dreamer, a businessman and a son-of-a-bitch&amp;quot; -Peter MacArthur&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/ptarkkonen/status/295095179155742720"&gt;Tweet from Petteri Tarkkonen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quote suggests that there are several distinct roles that have to
be present in a group for any endeavour to be succesfull.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These tree roles correspond to those of the wizard, the king and the
warrior that Tony Robbins used in his pattern of indirect negotiation
during an intervention at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rmtcenter.com/creating-leadership-in-times-of-crisis/"&gt;a seminar on september 11th 2001&lt;/a&gt;.
The only role that is missing is 'the fool'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fool is the only one that can redicule anyone, including the king,
and go unpunished. This role is crucial in limiting unrealistic ambitions,
yes-men and misleading advisors. With mild or not-so-mild humor he pulls
you back into reality, gets both your feet firmly on the ground and
maybe even slaps reality straight in your face.
The role of the fool is extremely underappreciated in a corporate culture
that relies on heavily paid consultants who do not dare to risk their precious
billable hours by pinching illusions and unrealistc ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former manager of mine used this mantra:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
You are either part of the solution or part of the problem.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to oppose this with another observation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
If you cannot solve the problem you can still make good money by
prolonging it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still in many organisations external consultants are far better paid than
regular staff.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="quotes"></category></entry></feed>